Welcome to my CV

- CV en Español
- CV in English

Professional Summary

Professional with over 20 years of experience in software development and Big Data architecture, having worked in sectors such as banking, telecommunications, healthcare, and advertising. Expert in building high-performance platforms and solutions using technologies like Spark, Kafka, Cloudera, AWS, Spring, and Elasticsearch. I have led teams and projects in both startups and large corporations, with a focus on agile methodologies.

I have experience in healthcare information systems (HL7, HIS), large-scale data analysis, process development, and data visualization and analysis tools.

Telecommunications Engineer with a Master's in Big Data & Visual Analytics, complemented by training in various technologies with a B1 level of English.

Professional Experience

Tecdata - Big Data Architect

(February 2022 - Present) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Development framework for Spark process execution.
 - Data availability for project teams.
 - Platform operation.
- Technologies: Spark3 (Java API), Cloudera, HIVE, ORC, Kafka, S3, AWS, S3, Schema Registry.

Stratio - Software Engineer

(April 2019 - February 2022) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Analysis and development of backoffice processes for Carrefour to run on Cloudera.
 - Analysis and development of APIs for Sanitas medical application.
- **Technologies:** Cloudera, Spark, HIVE, Apache Kudu, Spring Microservices, Saga Pattern, Kafka, HL7, HIS.

$\mathbf{Synergy} \,\, \mathbf{Inc} - \mathbf{CTO}$

(May 2018 - April 2019) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Technology lead for research.app architecture. Built the microservices layer of the application and deployed it on AWS / GCE.
- Technologies: REST API (Spring, JWT), AKKA agents, Redis, Elasticsearch, PostgreSQL, Websockets, AWS (Codecommit, ECS, S3, Cloudfront, Cloudwatch, Cloudformation, Elasticsearch, RDS, EC2), GCE (Kubernetes Engine, Compute Engine, SQL).

GFT - Development Engineer

(September 2016 – May 2018) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Developed microservices for Bankia's client applications and components for the Big Data area.
- **Technologies:** Logstash, Kafka, Redis, Elasticsearch, Kibana, Springboot, REST API, Docker.

Keedio - Big Data Engineer

(February 2014 - September 2016) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Experience in using different Big Data technologies for data ingestion, processing, and storage with Flume, Spark, Storm, Kafka, MongoDB, Redis, or ElasticSearch, and data analysis with tools like Kibana or Zeppelin and graphical libraries like D3, leaflet, echarts, or Datamaps.
 - Evolved Apache Zeppelin by adding features, enhancing graphical capabilities, and interpreters (formerly KATA).
 - Implemented REST APIs with SpringMVC on Azure.
- Technologies: Flume, Logstash, Kafka, Storm, Spark, Scala, Zeppelin, D3, DocumentDB, Redis, Elasticsearch, Kibana, HDFS, Map-Reduce, AngularJS, Springboot, REST API.

Mepaban – Incident Management Department

(August 2013 - February 2014) | Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Proactive analysis of incidents to identify root causes:
 - * Study of past incidents.
 - * Analysis of related incidents as problem patterns.

Media Investments – Partner/CTO

(November 2012 - August 2013) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Defined the technological strategy and was responsible for the MIP platform, focused on buying and selling advertising in media. Startup launch, business model definition.
- Technologies: PaaS Openshift, Pusher, Mailgun, MongoDB.

Skybus - Software Architect / Project Manager

(August 2009 - October 2012) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Defined the work environment tailored to the project's needs, including the work methodology for the entire development cycle (requirements, functional analysis, technical analysis, and testing), applying agile principles like Scrum or XP, configuration management, planning, and monitoring, ensuring product quality.
- Requirements gathering, functional and technical analysis, and component development.
- Implemented the basic platform using J2EE technologies, integrating embedded devices based on .NET and Android, processes executed on the CESVIMA Supercomputer, and rich applications in FLEX.
- The project received prestigious awards, being a finalist at IBM SmartCamp, winner of the LivingLabs Global Awards 2012, and a finalist at White Bull 2011.
- **Technologies:** JEMS (JBoss Architecture), JBoss messaging, BlazeDS (Flex client integration and JBoss AS), EJB3.0, .NET, C, evolutionary algorithms (genetic and VNS).

Tecnalis Solution Provider - Software Architect

(February 2007 - August 2009) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Middleware analysis and construction for an Internet gaming platform. Requirements gathering, solution definition and alternatives, and implementation. High availability and fault tolerance solutions (JBoss, Linux Virtual Server).
- Technologies: JEMS (JBoss Architecture), JBoss messaging, JBoss Cache, OpenCMS (web content management system), OpenAMF (Flex client integration and JBoss AS), EJB3.0, Enterprise Architect, LVS.

INDRA – Functional Analyst

(March 2005 - February 2007) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Requirements gathering and functional analysis for Mapfre Seguro's Surety and Credit division.
- **Technologies:** Oracle 10g, PLSQL-Developer, Enterprise Architect, Visual Basic 6, Erwin.

Cap Gemini - Senior Consultant

(March 2003 - February 2005) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Migration of Santa Lucía's Life and Non-Life Insurance Portfolio application. Migration application analysis. Design and development team coordination.
- Technologies: Oracle 9IAS Application Server, Informix, Together (UML), Excelerator (Jourdon methodology), Jbuilder 8, Pbuilder, C, Topend and GDMN middleware, Struts 1.1.

Algor Consultoría y Sistemas - Analyst

(December 2001 - March 2003) | Valladolid

• Responsibilities:

- Participated in various projects for Telefónica (Third Party Channels) and JCyL (Learn to Start, Early Age Hearing Detection, and CERA), designing and implementing web portals using Java technologies.
- **Technologies:** Java (JSPs and Servlets), Tomcat, JavaScript, HTML, Oracle 8i, EJB, JDeveloper 9i, EA (UML analysis tool), patterns: MVC, DAO, ValueListIterator.

Dharma Ingeniería – Analyst Consultant

(May 2001 - November 2001) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

- Designed and implemented a GIS viewer using Java technologies for Telefónica I+D.
- Technologies: Java, Oracle 9i.

Felizidades Network – Development and Research Resources Department

(March 2000 - May 2001) | Madrid

• Responsibilities:

 Designed, developed, and implemented the site felizidades.com.
Business model, prospecting and negotiating potential alliances (myalert.com, submarino.com, ...). • **Technologies:** JSP, Servlets, Java 1.2, JavaBeans, Allaire JRUN Web Server.

Grupo Delta Ingeniería – Development Department

(November 1999 – March 2000) | Tres Cantos, Madrid

- Responsibilities:
 - Developed a SCADA application for a RENFE railway hub.
- Technologies: C.

Education

- Telecommunications Engineer Universidad Alfonso X El Sabio
- Master in Big Data & Visual Analytics Universidad de La Rioja

Other complementary courses

- AWS Cloud Practitioner Essentials edX
- Big Data Architecture SEPE
- Home Automation and Digital Home SEPE
- Remote Sensing Applied to Precision Agriculture SEPE
- Java Development and OO Methodology Universidad Autónoma de Madrid
- SCO Unix Sema Madrid
- C++ Sema Madrid
- J2EE Architecture Indra
- Scrum Manager Scrummanager.net

Languages

- Spanish Native
- English B1

5